<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The haven of the afflicted A sermon preached in the Cathedral Church of Gloucester Aug. 10. 1613. By Sebastian Benefield Doctor of Divinity and fellow of C.C.C. in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849401</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849401</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14545</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14545)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1266:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The haven of the afflicted A sermon preached in the Cathedral Church of Gloucester Aug. 10. 1613. By Sebastian Benefield Doctor of Divinity and fellow of C.C.C. in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14545:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14545:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HAVEN OF THE AFFLICTED. A SERMON PREACHED IN THE CATHEDRAL CHVRCH OF GLOVCESTER <hi>Aug.</hi> 10. 1613.</p>
            <p>BY SEBASTIAN BENEFIELD Doctor of Divinity and fellow of C.C.C. <hi>in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 119.71.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>It is good for me that I haue been afflicted, that I might learne thy ſtatutes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14545:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14545:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN CHRIST <hi>MILES SMYTH</hi> BY THE DIVINE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIDENCE L. BISHOP OF <hi>GLOVCESTER</hi> GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT REVEREND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>little Sermon</hi> preached by your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the chiefe <hi>Citie</hi> of that <hi>Shire,</hi> wherein I firſt drew breath, now ſeeth the light. The religious deſires of ſome of my Countrymen there, wiſhing, that what I then vttered might not through obliuion periſh in the aire, haue brought it forth. Now they, who <hi>heard it,</hi> may <hi>record it;</hi> they who <hi>heard it not,</hi> may <hi>read it;</hi> all, I hope, wil be <hi>ſatiſfyed.</hi> My then endeavours were to arme my ſelfe, and that <hi>devout Auditorie</hi> with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence againſt the day of affliction; that day,
<pb facs="tcp:14545:3"/> which we muſt looke for, if we be the ſonnes of our Heauenly Father. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Euſtochium</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>Quis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum ſine certamine coronatus eſt? Quaere, &amp; inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſingulos adverſa perpeſſos; ſolus Salomon in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litijs fuit, &amp; forſitan ideò corruit:</hi> Who of all the Saints was ever crowned without a combat? Seeke, and thou ſhalt finde, that every one of them ſuffered aduerſities; onely <hi>Salomon</hi> was lulled in delights, and therefore <hi>perchance</hi> hee periſhed. It is but FORSITAN, <hi>perchance</hi> he periſhed. His booke called <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> or the <hi>Preacher,</hi> argueth his <hi>repentance,</hi> and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me of his <hi>remiſſion</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> with the LORD. And why might not <hi>Salomon</hi> in his time be, as many in our time are, inwardly <hi>in conſcience</hi> for ſinne <hi>afflicted?</hi> It's true; the <hi>ſtone</hi> hath no honourable place in <hi>a faire building</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe it be much <hi>hewed</hi> and <hi>hammered;</hi> neither can wee the liuely <hi>ſtones</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Church</hi> haue any place of credit <hi>in the Celeſtiall building</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we, like the <hi>chiefe corner stone,</hi> Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, bee <hi>hewed</hi> and <hi>hammered</hi> with adverſitie. To the patient enduring whereof this little
<pb facs="tcp:14545:3"/> Sermon hath a deſire to perſwade. Giue it <hi>(My good Lord)</hi> your fauourable countenance, that it may cheerefully goe abroad: and the Author of it ſhall heartely wiſh to your L. much encreaſe of grace and honour, with a daily influence of bleſſings from Heaven vpon your gouernment in the Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my study in <hi>CORPVS CHRISTI COLLEGE in OXFORD,</hi> 
                  <date>Auguſt 27, 1613.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>YOVR LORDSHIPS <hi>in all Christian duty to be commanded</hi> SEBASTIAN BENEFIELD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation_from_Augustine">
            <pb facs="tcp:14545:4"/>
            <head>
               <bibl>Auguſt. Enarrat. in Pſal. 97. Vulgat.</bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">QVid ſibi volunt <hi>tubae ductiles?</hi> —<hi>Ductiles tubae</hi> aereae ſunt, <hi>tundendo producuntur.</hi> Si <hi>tundendo,</hi> ergo <hi>vapulando</hi> eritis <hi>tubae ductiles,</hi> ad laudem Dei <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductae.</hi> Si cum tribulamini proficiatis, tribulatio <hi>tunſio,</hi> profectus <hi>productio</hi> eſt <hi>Tuba ductilis.</hi> erat Iob, quando repentè percuſſus tantis damnis &amp; orbitate filiorum, tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione illâ tantae tribulationis factus <hi>tuba ductilis,</hi> ſonuit: <hi>Dominus dedit, Dominus abſtulit; — ſit nomen Domini benedictum.</hi>
               </q> THAT IS,
<q xml:lang="eng" rend="roman">VVHat is meant by thoſe <hi>long trumpets? Long trumpets</hi> are of braſſe, and are by <hi>hammering lengthned.</hi> If by <hi>hammering,</hi> then by <hi>beating</hi> you ſhall be <hi>long trumpets, lengthned</hi> to praiſe God. If, when you are afflicted, you profit, your tribulation is your <hi>hammering,</hi> your profit that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth thereby, is your <hi>lengthning.</hi> Iob was a <hi>long trumpet,</hi> when hee was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſtriken with the loſſes of his ſubſtance and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Being made by that <hi>hammering</hi> of ſo great a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, <hi>a longe trumpet,</hi> he ſounded out: <hi>The Lord hath giuen, the Lord hath taken away,—bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14545:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>AMOS 3.6.</bibl>
                  <p>Shall there be evill in a city, and the <hi>LORD</hi> hath not done it?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian profeſſion</hi> is by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, <hi>1. Cor. 9.24.</hi> &amp;, <hi>Heb. 12.1.</hi> reſembled to a <hi>race.</hi> The run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this <hi>race</hi> are the <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of Chriſtianity,</hi> men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of all rankes, all <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Stadium eſt haec vita morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus; híc conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus, vt alibi coronemur. <hi>Hieron. ep. ad Euſtochium.</hi>
               </note> We al runne, <hi>non pedum celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, ſed virtute, pietate, fide:</hi> our running is, not by ſwiftneſſe of foot, but by vertue, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and faith. And we runne for a <hi>price.</hi> The <hi>price</hi> is a <hi>crowne.</hi> No<note n="*" place="margin">A. Gellius Nect. Attic. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>murall,</hi> no <hi>ovall,</hi> no <hi>civil,</hi> no <hi>triumphal,</hi> no <hi>obſidional crowne;</hi> no ſuch <hi>crowne,</hi> as worthy champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of old contended for; no <hi>crowne</hi> of <hi>graſſe,</hi> no <hi>crowne</hi> of <hi>oliue,</hi> no <hi>crowne</hi> of <hi>oake,</hi> no <hi>crowne</hi> of <hi>gold.</hi> Al theſe were vile and contemptible in regard of the <hi>crowne,</hi> which we run for. They were all tranſitory and corruptible; but the <hi>crowne</hi> which we runne for, is a <hi>crowne of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. S. Peter</hi> in his <hi>1. Epiſt. chap. 5. ver. 4.</hi> calleth it τὸν ἀ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>μαράντινον τῆς δόξης στέφανον, <hi>a crown of glory, that fadeth not. S. Paule, 1. Cor. 9.25.</hi> calleth it τὸν στέφανον ἄφθαρτον, <hi>an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible crowne.</hi> Now the place where we <hi>runne</hi> for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14545:5"/> this incorruptible and never fading <hi>crowne</hi> is, <hi>civitas huius mundi,</hi> the city of this world. Here we<note n="*" place="margin">Magnis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imicorum cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundamur agminibus; hoſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plena ſunt omnia. Hieron vbi. ſuprà.</note> meete with many ſtops; many lets, many hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations vpon temptations do even ſwarme before vs, behinde vs, beſide vs, round about vs. Temptations of proſperity, temptations of adverſity, temptations of hereſie, theſe ſtand in the ſtreets, like<note n="a" place="margin">Gen 3.24.</note> the flaming ſword, to ſtop our way to Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>The greateſt obſtacle or impediment, moſt likely to overthrow vs in this <hi>race,</hi> is the temptation of the croſſe, the temptation of adverſity. The godly man, he who hath <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>promiſes as well of the life that now is, as of that which is to come,</hi> as well<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 28 1. &amp;c. Lev. 26.3. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>corporall,</hi> as <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> if he be depreſſed and kept vnder in diſgrace and miſery, while the wicked man before his face is highly adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to honour &amp; preferment, how is he diſcouraged? how diſcomforted? With this temptation was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> exerciſed. For when he ſaw the proſperity of the wicked, and conſidered, that <hi>they were not afflicted like other men,</hi> that <hi>they encreaſed in riches,</hi> that <hi>whatſoever they took in hand, it went well forward; his feet were almoſt gone, his ſteps had well-nigh ſlipt.</hi> It is his owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Pſal. 73.2.</hi> Did this temptation ſo farre prevaile with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>a man after Gods owne heart?</hi> How ſhall the reſt of the <hi>Godly</hi> withſtand it? Behold for them an anchor, able to keep them, that they be not overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the waues of this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation; even the words of my text,
<q>Shall there be evill in a city, and the <hi>LORD</hi> hath not done it?</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14545:5"/>
            <p>Here are ſeaven interogations together without any interruption. This is the ſeaventh, and is like the reſt. It beareth the forme of an Interrogation, but is for matter a vehement Aſſeveration. It's vſuall with the Scriptures then to propound a matter by way of queſtion, when they will moſt of all affirme it. Gen. 18.14. the LORD ſaith to <hi>Abraham: Is any thing too hard for the</hi> LORD? It is as if he had ſaid; al things are eaſie with the LORD; there is nothing impoſſible, nothing too hard for him. Mar. 12.24. <hi>Ieſus</hi> anſwering the <hi>Sadduces</hi> ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Doe yee not therefore erre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yee knowe not the Scriptures, neither the power of God?</hi> It is, as if he had ſaid: doubtleſſe yee therefore erre becauſe yee knowe not the Scriptures, neither the power of God. 1. Cor. 10.16. <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The bread which we breake, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> It is, as if he had ſaid: <hi>The bread which wee breake is the communion of the body of Chriſt.</hi> Many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of like nature I might produce: But by theſe wee ſee, that an <hi>Interrogation</hi> vſeth to be put from an <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;</hi> as in my text,
<q>Shall there bee evill in a city, and the <hi>LORD</hi> hath not done it?</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is as if our Prophet had ſaid: <hi>There ſhall be no evill in a city, but the</hi> LORD <hi>will doe it.</hi> Or, <hi>whatſoever evil is in a city, the</hi> LORD <hi>hath done it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> happyly will ſome ſay, as thoſe fleſhly hearers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to <hi>Chriſt, Ioh. 6.60.</hi> When <hi>Chriſt</hi> had told them, that they were <hi>to eate his fleſh,</hi> &amp; <hi>to drinke his blood,</hi> elſe they ſhould not liue. <hi>Durus eſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14545:6"/> hic ſermo,</hi> This is a hard ſaying; who can endure to heare it? Shall there be no evil in a city, but the LORD will doe it? but he hath done it? <hi>Durus ſermo;</hi> This is a hard ſaying.</p>
            <p>This ſtumbling blocke, this ſtone of offence will eaſily be remoued, if you will bee pleaſed to conſider with me three circumſtances expreſſed in the letter of my text: <hi>Quis, Quid, Vbi.</hi> An <hi>Agent,</hi> an <hi>Action,</hi> The <hi>place</hi> of performance. The <hi>Agent</hi> is the LORD, the <hi>Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is a <hi>doing of evill,</hi> the <hi>place</hi> where this action is to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, is a <hi>City. Shall there be evill in a city, and the</hi> LORD <hi>hath not done it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Follow me, I beſeech you, in theſe three, I will paſſe them over as briefly, and as plainely as I may. If in my diſcourſe I ſhall ſeeme for a while ſomewhat thorny, or perplexed, helpe me with your attention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall there be evill in a city, &amp; the</hi> LORD <hi>hath not done it?</hi>] The firſt circumſtance to bee now conſidered is <hi>Quis.</hi> The <hi>Agent.</hi> My text cals him IEHOVAH.</p>
            <p>IEHOVAH! It is the moſt proper name of God. No creature is made partaker of it; nor man, nor Angel. It betokeneth firſt the eſſence of God, ſecondly the truth and complement of his promiſes. Firſt it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that God is <hi>verè</hi> τὸ ὂν: <hi>à quo</hi> πάντα τὰ ὄντα ; that God is ſo of himſelfe, that<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 11.36.</note> 
               <hi>of him, and through him, and to him are all things.</hi> Secondly it ſignifieth, that God is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faithful in his promiſes. From whence two things ſhould deeply, and perpetually bee faſtned in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of every Chriſtian: one is, that our God is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verliuing God, is the chiefeſt good, is the author of all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14545:6"/> good, and is therefore alwaies, and aboue al things to be loued: the other is, that our God is ever true in his promiſes, and therefore that our whole truſt muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lie on him. For he only is IEHOVAH: IEHOVAH is his name for ever, it is his <hi>memoriall vnto all generations.</hi> So it is called, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.<hi>15.</hi> and <hi>Hoſ. 12.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This our <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> IEHOVAH, who is of himſelfe alone, and is only true in all his ſayings, hee is not that God of thoſe ſhameleſſe blaſphemers, the<note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt, de Haereſib. c. 46.</note> 
               <hi>Manichees</hi> and<note n="g" place="margin">Ibid. c. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Marcionites,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Zanchius de Attribut. Dei. lib. 4. cap. 1. qu. 1. theſ 4.</note> 
               <hi>Deus malus, à quo ſit omne malum,</hi> an <hi>evill God</hi> from whom commeth all evill. Our <hi>God</hi> is no ſuch God; there is no <hi>evill</hi> in him, there proceeds no evill fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: he is wholly<note n="i" place="margin">Pſ. 33.5. &amp; 73.1. &amp; 103.11, 17. &amp; 136.1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>good: good</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>In ſe</hi> Deꝰ bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n' eſt <hi>ſuâ eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, &amp; ſummè.</hi> Pola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Syntag. Theol. lib. 2. cap 20.</note> of himſelfe; &amp; by his eſſence. Now, if <hi>hony,</hi> of its owne nature and eſſence <hi>ſweet,</hi> hath no <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> in it; if the <hi>Sunne</hi> of its owne nature and eſſence <hi>light,</hi> hath no <hi>darkneſſe</hi> in it; without doubt <hi>God</hi> of himſelfe, of his owne nature &amp; eſſence <hi>good,</hi> hath no <hi>evill</hi> in him. Wee confeſſe with <hi>David, Pſal. 5.4.</hi> O our God, <hi>thou art not a God, that hath pleaſure in wickedneſſe, neither ſhall any evill dwell with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, <hi>Quis,</hi> who this <hi>Agent</hi> is. It is IEHOVAH, <hi>the</hi> Lord <hi>our God,</hi> whoſe being is of himſelfe, who is <hi>true</hi> in all his ſayings, who is abſolutely <hi>good,</hi> in whom there is no ſtaine of <hi>evill.</hi> Such is the <hi>Agent.</hi> The next circumſtance is <hi>Quid,</hi> the <hi>Action,</hi> a <hi>doing of evill; Shall there be evill in a city, and the</hi> LORD <hi>hath not done it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The naturaliſt ſaith;<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>A good tree bringeth forth good fruit:</hi> the Philoſopher ſaith; <hi>Omne</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Ariſt. 2. Phyſ. Aquin. 2. Diſt. 18. qu. 2. Art. 1. ad. 4. Zanch. de At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trib. l. 2. cap. 7. qu. 3.</note> 
               <hi>agens agit ſibi ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi> Such as the <hi>Agent</hi> is, ſuch is the <hi>Action:</hi> if the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14545:7"/> be <hi>good,</hi> the <hi>Action</hi> cannot be <hi>evil.</hi> How then is it, that God of himſelfe and abſolutely <hi>Good,</hi> is here, in my text, noted, for a <hi>doer of evill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer herevnto wee muſt with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin cap. 26. contra Adimantum Manichaeum</hi> diſtinguiſh of <hi>evils:</hi> there is <hi>malum, quod facit homo,</hi> and <hi>malum, quod pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> there is an <hi>evill</hi> which man doth, and there is an <hi>evill</hi> which man ſuffereth: the firſt is <hi>ſinne,</hi> the other is <hi>the puniſhment of ſinne,</hi> of this, not of that, muſt God be ſaid to be the <hi>doer.</hi> This diſtinction is more plainely delivered by <hi>Tertullian, contra Marcion. lib. 2. cap. 14.</hi> There is <hi>malum delicti,</hi> and <hi>malum ſupplicij,</hi> there is <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum culpae,</hi> and <hi>malum poenae;</hi> there is an <hi>evill</hi> of ſinne, &amp; an <hi>evill</hi> of paine, <hi>Suum cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> parti definimus autorem,</hi> ſaith that <hi>Father, malorum quidem peccati &amp; culpae Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum, malorum verò ſupplicij &amp; poenae Deum creatorem.</hi> Of the <hi>evills of ſinne</hi> and <hi>fault</hi> the Devill is the author, but in the <hi>evils</hi> of <hi>paine</hi> and <hi>puniſhment,</hi> wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the hand of God the Creatour.</p>
            <p>This diſtinction of <hi>evils,</hi> ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Annot. 82. in locum Tertulliani.</note> 
               <hi>Pamelius,</hi> is worth the noting againſt <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his followers; as if <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> or the reſt, who maintaine the truth of that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which <hi>Calvin</hi> profeſſed, denied this diſtinction of <hi>Evils,</hi> to make God the <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>author</hi> of <hi>ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This horrible blaſphemie and impietie, wherewith<note n="o" place="margin">De amiſſ. Grat. &amp; ſtatu reccati lib. 2. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Octavâ ratione.</note> 
               <hi>Campian,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Defenſione. praefationum Bellarm. Tom 1 pag. 5, &amp; 6.</note> 
               <hi>Gretſer,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Tom. 1. Opuſc. 3. de autore pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati p. 98.</note> 
               <hi>Becan,</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Bernard. Dörhoff A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podix 1. cap. 3. pag. 32. Carol. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banius Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. fidei controverſ. lib. 2. cap. 3. pag. 121. &amp;c. Matth. Kelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in his Reply to Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffes anſwer to the Survey 5. booke pag. 356. &amp;c.</note> other of that rabble, haue branded vs, I haue elſewhere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted in a Sermon vpon <hi>Hoſ. 10.2.</hi> wherein I confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med two poſitions.</p>
            <p>One: <hi>There is a degree of ſome forwarder diſpoſition of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14545:7"/> God, in the actions of vnrighteous men, then his bare tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other: <hi>Though God bee a worker in the workes of the wicked, yet is the will of the wicked thereby no way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled.</hi> Whence followeth this concluſion; <hi>God is not to any conſtruction, the cauſe or author of ſinne.</hi> This we affirme in our bookes, we teach in our pulpits, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in our Schooles.</p>
            <p>We ſay, and our adverſaries will ſay no leſſe, that God is the author of all actions in the world; that hee is the author of every motion within vs. <hi>In him we liue and moue, and haue our being, Act. 17.28.</hi> without him we liue not, we moue not, we haue no being. Yet wee ſay that ſinne, is wholly and only of man himſelfe; we cannot challenge God for any part thereof.</p>
            <p>Diſtinguiſh then the <hi>accident</hi> from the <hi>ſubiect,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the <hi>ſinne of the action</hi> from the <hi>action it ſelfe;</hi> God in the one ſhal be glorified, and man ſhal be iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned for the other. <hi>God is not to any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the cauſe, or author of ſinne.</hi> Yet, you ſee my text char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him, as if he were <hi>the cauſe &amp; author of Evill. Shall there be evill in a city, and the</hi> Lord <hi>hath not done it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Evill!</hi> If by <hi>evill</hi> you will vnderſtande according to my former diſtinctions <hi>(malum poenae, malum ſupplicij, malum, quod homo patitur,</hi> which you may call, <hi>malum afflictionis)</hi> if by <hi>Evill</hi> you will vnderſtand the <hi>evill</hi> of paine, the <hi>evill</hi> of puniſhment, the <hi>evill</hi> of affliction, you haue the meaning of my Prophet: <hi>Shall there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Evill</hi>] Any <hi>evill</hi> of paine, puniſhment, or afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Shall there be any</hi> ſuch <hi>Evill in a city, and the</hi> Lord <hi>hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14545:8"/> not done it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe now brought diſtinctions of <hi>evill</hi> may ſerue for the vnfolding of other texts of Scripture: of that, <hi>Eſay 45.7. I, the</hi> Lord, <hi>create Evill;</hi> &amp; that, <hi>Lament. 3.38. Out of the mouth of the moſt high proceedeth Evill;</hi> &amp; that <hi>Ion. 3.10. God repented of the Evill, that he had ſaid, hee would do vnto them.</hi> By <hi>Evill</hi> in all thoſe places, as here in my text, we are to vnderſtand the Evil of paine, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and affliction.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Evill</hi> of paine, puniſhment, and affliction! Why <hi>Euil?</hi> Doubtleſſe whatſoever paine, puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or affliction befalleth vs, it is <hi>good.</hi> 1. Becauſe it is laide vpon vs, by God, who is of himſelfe, and abſolutelie <hi>good.</hi> 2. Becauſe it is iuſt: and what is iuſt, muſt needs be <hi>good.</hi> 3. Becauſe it tendeth to the glory of God, and the ſalvation of the elect; and who will deny this to be <hi>good?</hi> For theſe reaſons whatſoever paine, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or affliction may befall vs, it is <hi>good.</hi> Why then is it in my text, and elſewhere noted by the name of <hi>Evill?.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is ſo noted, becauſe in our ſenſe and feeling it is <hi>Evill.</hi> Things may bee tearmed <hi>Evill</hi> two manner of waies: ſome are <hi>Euill indeed, and of their owne nature;</hi> in this rancke we muſt place our ſinnes: ſome are <hi>Evill,</hi> not indeed and of their owne nature, but <hi>in regard of our ſenſe, apprehenſion, and eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> &amp; in this ranke we muſt place whatſoever, paine, puniſhment, or afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God layeth vpon vs in this life for our ſinnes. I ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the <hi>Euill</hi> in my text, is <hi>indeed good,</hi> but <hi>improperly Evill;</hi> it is <hi>good in its owne nature,</hi> but <hi>Evill</hi> only, as wee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14545:8"/> call <hi>Euill,</hi> whatſoever liketh vs not, or is not for our eaſe. Thus farre haue you my ſecond circumſtance, <hi>Quid,</hi> the <hi>Action,</hi> a <hi>doing of Euill: Shall there be euill in a city, and the</hi> Lord <hi>hath not done it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third circumſtance is <hi>Vbi,</hi> the <hi>place</hi> where this <hi>Action</hi> is performed. My text cals it <hi>a City. Shal there be Evill in a City] In Civitatibus,</hi> in Cities, ſo <hi>Lyranus</hi> expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it. <hi>In Civitate aliquâ,</hi> in any City, it is <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerus</hi> his expoſition. I ſay, <hi>in Civitate huius mundi,</hi> in the City of this world.</p>
            <p>This vniverſe, &amp; admirable frame of Nature wherin IEHOVAH, the LORD, <hi>our God,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 97.1. &amp; 91.1.</note> raigneth, conſiſteth of two Cities: the one is,<note n="u" place="margin">Auguſt. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. l 2. c. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Civitas Dei,</hi> the city of God, the other is,<note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt. de temp. ſerm. 106.</note> 
               <hi>Civitas huius mundi,</hi> the city of this world. The one is<note n="y" place="margin">Aug. de Civ. Dei lib 14. cap. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Celeſtiall,</hi> the other is <hi>Terrene;</hi> the one is <hi>of the</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Aug. de ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizandis rudib. l. 1. c. 19</note> 
               <hi>Saints,</hi> the other <hi>of the wicked;</hi> the one is<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. Enar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat in Pſ. 61.</note> 
               <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the other is <hi>Babylon.</hi> In the firſt, that moſt glorious city of God, and his Saints, the Celeſtiall <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, all teares</hi> are <hi>wiped away from the eies</hi> of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens; there is neither <hi>death,</hi> nor <hi>ſorrow,</hi> nor <hi>crying,</hi> nor <hi>paine, Revel. 21.4.</hi> There is no <hi>Evill</hi> there; no not the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of affliction.</hi> Wherefore that <hi>City,</hi> is not the <hi>City</hi> in my text.</p>
            <p>In the other <hi>City,</hi> the <hi>City of this world,</hi> the <hi>Terrene city,</hi> the <hi>city</hi> peſtered with the wicked, <hi>Babylon,</hi> great <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>city of confuſion,</hi> there is no ſure repoſe for the Godly there. There may they become a<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ 79 4.</note> 
               <hi>reproach to their neighbours,</hi> there may they be <hi>a ſcorne, and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to them, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they liue;</hi> there may they<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 88.9.</note> mourne daily by reaſon of affliction. For even the Godly, who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14545:9"/> are<note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. de civitate Dei lib. 15. cap. 1.</note> by grace <hi>cives ſurſum,</hi> Citizens aboue, citizens of the ſupernall and Celeſtiall City of God, they are alſo by grace <hi>peregrini deorſum,</hi> pilgrimes, or ſtrangers here below, in this Terrene city, the city of this world. Here muſt they paſſe through many <hi>evils;</hi> here muſt they be cut, hewen, and ſquared, with ſundry <hi>tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſickneſſes,</hi> and <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> before they can bee made fit and liuely ſtones for the heavenly <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue wee found out the <hi>City</hi> in my text; it is this <hi>Terrene City,</hi> the <hi>City of this world;</hi> and this was my third circumſtance. <hi>Vbi,</hi> the circumſtance of the <hi>place,</hi> where the <hi>Agent</hi> performeth his <hi>Action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the meaning of my text is plaine. <hi>Shall there be evil in a city; and the</hi> LORD <hi>hath not done it? Shal there be evill</hi>] Any <hi>evill</hi> of paine, puniſhment, or affliction, <hi>In a City</hi>] Not only in this <hi>City,</hi> wherein wee are now aſſembled, but in <hi>any City,</hi> or other <hi>place</hi> of the whole world, in the <hi>city</hi> of this world, <hi>Shall there bee any</hi> ſuch <hi>evill</hi> any where, and <hi>the</hi> LORD <hi>hath not done it?</hi>] Or, as the diverſe reading is,<note n="e" place="margin">In the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of the new tranſlation.</note> 
               <hi>Shall not the</hi> LORD <hi>doe</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what? The doctrine from hence to be commended to your moſt ſerious and religious meditations, is,
<q>Whatſoeuer affliction befalleth any one any where in this world, it is from the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>affliction</hi> in this propoſition I vnderſtand the <hi>ſuffering</hi> of any thing, the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or <hi>cogitation</hi> whereof our nature ſhunneth. Whatſoever is any way <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> or <hi>offenſiue,</hi> to our humane nature, I call <hi>Afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The temptations of the fleſh, the world &amp; the Devil; the diſeaſes of the body, an infortunate husband or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14545:9"/> wife, rebellious children, vnthankfull friends, loſſe of goods, reproaches, ſclaunders, war, peſtilence, famine, impriſonment, death; every croſſe and paſſion, bodily or ghoſtly, proper to our ſelues, or appertaining to ſuch as are of our blood private or publike, ſecret or manifeſt, either by our owne deſerts gotten, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe impoſed vpon vs, I call <hi>Afflictions.</hi> In a word, all manner of miſeries, calamities, vexations, or moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in this life from the leaſt to the greateſt, from the paine of the little finger, to the very pangs of death, I call <hi>Afflictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two ſorts of men (ſhall I ſay, in this city? I ſay in the city of this world) there are two ſorts of men viſited with <hi>afflictions:</hi> the one, the Scriptures cal the <hi>reprobate;</hi> the other, the <hi>elect;</hi> they are the <hi>wicked,</hi> theſe the <hi>godly.</hi> Whatſoever <hi>Affliction</hi> befalleth the firſt ſort, the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> the <hi>wicked,</hi> it is, (as Divines call it) τιμωία, a <hi>puniſhment</hi> wherewith <hi>God</hi> as a <hi>fearefull iudge</hi> avengeth himſelfe vpon the <hi>wicked</hi> for their ſins; properly a <hi>puniſhment;</hi> a <hi>puniſhment</hi> inflicted on men <hi>ſinning,</hi> that the <hi>iuſtice</hi> of God may thereby bee <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the other ſort, with the <hi>Elect,</hi> with the <hi>Godly</hi> it is not ſo. Whatſoever afflictions befall them, they are not properly <hi>puniſhments</hi> for their ſinnes; they are more rightly called <hi>Croſſes. Puniſhments</hi> they cannot properly be called; becauſe whatſoever <hi>puniſhment</hi> is due to any of the <hi>Elect</hi> for their ſinnes, it's fully anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his actiue and paſſiue obedience, in his life and death. He is become our λύτρον, hee hath paid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14545:10"/> the price of our redemption, he hath fully ſatisfied for all our ſinnes; our ſinnes paſt, preſent, and to come. And therefore if any <hi>afflictions</hi> be vpon vs, we are not to call them properly <hi>puniſhments</hi> for our ſinnes; the name of <hi>croſſes</hi> will befit them better.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>croſſes</hi> of the godly are either παιδιεῖαι or δοχι<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>μα<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>αι, they are either <hi>chaſtiſements</hi> for our ſinnes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perpetrated, to make vs the more wary for the time to come, that we fall not againe into the ſame, or the like ſinnes; or they are <hi>trials,</hi> and <hi>exerciſes,</hi> of our faith, hope, charitie, patience, and other like Chriſtian vertues. Now all theſe fore-mentioned <hi>afflictions,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther properly <hi>puniſhments</hi> for ſinne, ſuch as are the <hi>afflictions</hi> of the <hi>wicked,</hi> or <hi>chaſtiſements,</hi> or <hi>trials,</hi> ſuch as are the <hi>afflictions</hi> of the <hi>Godly,</hi> they are all from the LORD according to the truth of my doctrine,
<q>Whatſoever affliction befalleth any one, any where in this world, it is from the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The LORD, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>primary cauſe</hi> of all <hi>afflictions,</hi> and of many the <hi>immediate cauſe.</hi> Of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall deluge, and <hi>floud of waters</hi> in the daies of <hi>Noah, Gen. 6.17.</hi> Of the <hi>burning</hi> of <hi>Sodom, Gomorah,</hi> and their ſiſter Cities, <hi>Gen. 19.24.</hi> Of the <hi>overthrow of Pharaohs hoſt in the midſt of the ſea, Exod. 14.27.</hi> Of the <hi>ſmiting of Nabal to death, 1. Sam. 25.38.</hi> of all theſe was God the <hi>immediate cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>afflictions</hi> it pleaſeth God to effect <hi>mediatè,</hi> by <hi>ſecundary,</hi> and <hi>inſtrumentall cauſes,</hi> by <hi>Angels,</hi> by <hi>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> by <hi>other creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt God <hi>afflicteth</hi> by <hi>Angels.</hi> By an <hi>Angel</hi> he ſmote
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14545:10"/> 
               <hi>Davids</hi> people, ſo that there died of the peſtilence <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Dan <hi>to</hi> Beerſheba, <hi>ſeauenty thouſand men, 2. Sam. 24.15.</hi> By an <hi>Angel</hi> he <hi>ſmote in the campe of the</hi> Aſſyrians, <hi>one hundred foureſcore and fiue thouſand, 2. King. 19.35.</hi> By an <hi>Angel</hi> he <hi>ſmote K. Herod,</hi> ſo that he <hi>died, Act. 12.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God <hi>afflicteth</hi> by <hi>men.</hi> Here might I tell you of the afflictions, wherewith God exerciſed his people Iſrael by <hi>Cuſhan-Riſhathaim K. of Meſopotamia for eight yeares, Iudg. 3.8.</hi> By the <hi>Midianites for ſeaven yeares, Iudg. 6.1.</hi> By the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and the <hi>Ammonites for eighteene yeares, Iudg. 10.8.</hi> By the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> againe for <hi>forty years, Iudg. 13.1.</hi> Here might I relate vnto you the many <hi>afflictions,</hi> wherewith God proved his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the people of <hi>Iudah,</hi> by ſending againſt them the <hi>Egyptians, Aſſyrians,</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans.</hi> The bookes of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles</hi> are copious in deſcribing them. I need not remember you of <hi>Aſhur, Eſai, 10.5.</hi> how there he is ſtiled the <hi>rod</hi> &amp; the <hi>ſtaffe of the wrath of God,</hi> to ſignifie, that he was <hi>organum, ſiue inſtrumentum Dei,</hi> the executioner of Gods vengeance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hypocrites. I will not hold you with any long narration of <hi>Attila,</hi> King of the <hi>Hunnes, Medes, Gotthes,</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> how in his title or <hi>inſcription</hi> he called himſelfe, <hi>metum orbis, flagellúm<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Dei,</hi> the terrour of the world, &amp; the ſcourge of God. I paſſe over the great <hi>Turke,</hi> whom you know now to bee the <hi>hammer</hi> of the world, and the <hi>rod</hi> of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Come we home vnto our ſelues. Here ſhal we find it made good, that by <hi>men</hi> God <hi>afflicteth men.</hi> Elſe why is it come to paſſe according to <hi>Ieremies</hi> words, chap.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14545:11"/> 9.4. that <hi>a neighbour deceiueth his neighbour,</hi> that a <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſupplanteth his brother?</hi> Why is it now according to <hi>Micah's</hi> words, chap. 7 6. that <hi>the ſonne diſhonoureth his father,</hi> that <hi>the daughter riſeth vp against her mother?</hi> Why are a<note n="f" place="margin">Micah 7 6. Matth 10.36.</note> 
               <hi>mans enimies</hi> now the <hi>men of his owne houſe?</hi> Why doth the corrupt Magiſtrate<note n="g" place="margin">Amos 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſel the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous for ſiluer, and the poore for a paire of ſhooes?</hi> Why doth the cruell Landlord<note n="h" place="margin">Amos 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>pant after the duſt of the earth on the head of his poore tenant?</hi> Why behold we in our cities <hi>biting vſurie,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Hab. 1.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>violence, oppreſsion, falſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling?</hi> Certainely God is even now pleaſed to <hi>afflict men</hi> by <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God <hi>afflicteth</hi> by <hi>other creatures</hi> alſo. This the ſtory of Gods viſitation vpon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians, Exod. chap. 8, 9, 10.</hi> maketh plaine vnto vs. There we finde that <hi>frogges, lice, flies, graſhoppers, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, haile, lightning, murraine, botches, and ſores,</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally avenge God vpon man &amp; beaſt in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Not in <hi>Egypt</hi> only, but every where elſe, thoſe &amp; other like creatures, as <hi>fire,</hi> and <hi>ſnow,</hi> and <hi>vapours,</hi> and <hi>ſtormy windes,</hi> doe fulfill what God commandeth. So ſaith the Spirit, <hi>Pſ. 148.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Infinite might I be in the proſecution of this point &amp; yet keepe my ſelfe within the limits of Sacred writ. But I may not dwell hereon. Only in ſumme I ſay; <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Agent</hi> in my text, is <hi>Deus exercituum,</hi> a God of hoſts. All creatures, <hi>Celeſtial, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial, Infernal,</hi> &amp; the reſt, that are either in the <hi>aire,</hi> or in <hi>water;</hi> they are all of <hi>Gods armie,</hi> and are ready to doe his Holy will. By theſe God <hi>afflicteth</hi> vs. Theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14545:11"/> are the <hi>inſtruments,</hi> but God is the <hi>author</hi> of our <hi>affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi> Thus is my doctrine eſtabliſhed,
<q>Whatſoever affliction befalleth any one any where in this world, it is from the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatſoever affliction</hi>] be it puniſhment, chaſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or triall, <hi>Befalleth any one</hi>] wicked or Godly, <hi>Any where in this world</hi>] either here or elſe where, in the city of this world, <hi>It is from the</hi> Lord] either immediatly and primarily of himſelfe, or mediatly and ſecundarily, by Angels, men, and other creatures, the inſtruments &amp; executioners of his holy and iuſt iudgements.</p>
            <p>This doctrine thus confirmed and explained is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable many waies.</p>
            <p>Firſt it may ſerue for reproofe of ſome olde Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the <hi>Coluthians,</hi> and <hi>Florinians.</hi> The<note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. de haereſ. cap. 65</note> 
               <hi>Coluthians</hi> affirmed, that <hi>God doth no evill,</hi> contrary to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent text and doctrine. The <hi>Florinians</hi> affirmed, that <hi>God createth evill,</hi> contrary to that, <hi>Gen. 1.31. God ſaw every thing, that he had made, and behold it was very good.</hi> Theſe two ſects of Hereticks are one againſt the other, but both againſt the dictates of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. S. <hi>Auſtine cap. 66. lib. de haereſib.</hi> hath fitted one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for both: <hi>Creat Deus mala, poenas iuſtiſsimas irro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando, quod Coluthus non videbat; non autem malas cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ando naturas, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſubſtantias, in quantum ſunt naturae, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſubſtantiae, vbi Florinus errabat.</hi> The ſumme of his anſwer is: God may bee ſaid to <hi>create evill,</hi> to <hi>doe evill,</hi> by laying vpon offenders iuſt puniſhments, which <hi>Coluthus</hi> ſaw not; but not by making evill natures and ſubſtances, which was <hi>Florinus</hi> his errour. God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14545:12"/> 
               <hi>evill,</hi> God <hi>doth evill;</hi> vnderſtand it not<note n="l" place="margin">Paulus de Palatio.</note> 
               <hi>de malo culpae &amp; criminu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but <hi>de punitione, poenâ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſcelerum,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it not of the <hi>evill</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Rupertus.</note> 
               <hi>of iniquitie,</hi> but of the <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of affliction,</hi> you are in right. For,
<q>Whatſoever affliction befalleth any one any where in this world, it is from the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Is it from the LORD? Then in the ſecond place this doctrine ſerueth to reproue ſuch, as doe volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and wilfully thruſt themſelues into <hi>afflictions,</hi> not expecting the good houre, when God ſhould lay his <hi>rod</hi> vpon them. The offenders in this kind are the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> ſuch as betake themſelues to the <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as they cal it,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>to beat themſelues naked with rods &amp; whips:</hi> ſuch as ſuperſtitiouſly<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>weare ſackcloath,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>goe barefoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>lie vpon the ground;</hi> thinking by theſe, and ſuch <hi>toies,</hi> to expiate their ſinnes, and to demerite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues eternall life.</p>
            <p>A vaile for this their hypocriſie they thinke they haue, in 1. Cor. 9.27. where S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>I keepe my body vnder, and bring it into ſubiection.</hi> The words are much ſtood on by <hi>Gretſer lib. 1. de Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cap. 4.</hi> Hee collecteth from them, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>diſcipline</hi> himſelfe, that is, did puniſh himſelfe with ſtrokes of rods or whips. For what elſe, ſaith hee, is ὑποπιάζειν, but to <hi>beate with mightie ſtrokes?</hi> And what is that, but <hi>facere diſciplinam,</hi> to vſe <hi>diſcipline</hi> vpon himſelfe.</p>
            <p>This vaile we eaſily take from them. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> takes his ὑποπιάζω <hi>tropically,</hi> as <hi>tranſlated</hi> from the manner of fight betweene a champion, and his antagoniſt.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14545:12"/> But what is this to the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> purpoſe, who takes it <hi>literally?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> kept <hi>his body vnder,</hi> and brought <hi>it into ſubiection.</hi> I graunt it. So ſhould we after his example. Jt's our parts alſo ὑποπιάζειν: it's our parts to <hi>keepe our bodies vnder, to bring them into ſubiection.</hi> The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not, that wee ſhould afflict and macerate our bodies with <hi>whips,</hi> with <hi>ſcourges,</hi> with <hi>hairecloths,</hi> with <hi>lying vpon the ground,</hi> and the like; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> did not do ſo; but the meaning is, that we ſhould <hi>ſubdue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the old man</hi> within vs, that wee ſhould <hi>keepe vnder the body of ſinne</hi> within vs, that we ſhould <hi>bring into ſubiection the corrupt nature</hi> within vs, that thus <hi>mortified in the fleſh,</hi> we may bee <hi>quickned by the Spirit,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>1. Epiſt. chap. 3.18.</hi> Thus <hi>mortified</hi> in the one, and <hi>quickned</hi> by the other, wee ſhall bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with patience to beare whatſoever <hi>affliction</hi> ſhal light vpon vs, being well aſſured, that every ſuch <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is from the</hi> LORD, according to the truth of my doctrine,
<q>Whatſoever affliction befalleth any one, any where in this world, it's from the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Is it ſo beloued? Then in the third place, this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſerueth to confute the vaine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Fortune,</hi> wherevnto, like the Philoſophers of old, ſome carnal ignorant people now adaies vſe to aſcribe ſuch their <hi>afflictions,</hi> whereof they ſee not an apparant cauſe. If by <hi>fire,</hi> by <hi>lightning,</hi> by <hi>tempeſts,</hi> by <hi>windes,</hi> by <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> by <hi>vnſeaſonable weather,</hi> by <hi>theeues,</hi> or otherwiſe, they receaue loſſe, they aſcribe all to Fortune; <hi>quaſi
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14545:13"/> Deus otium coleret in coelo, &amp; non curaret res humanas,</hi> as if they were to hold it for an article of their beleefe, that God liueth idlely in Heaven, and hath no care of mans affaires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noli fortunam, quae non eſt, dicere caecam.</hi> Fooliſh man! why doſt thou for thy loſſes accuſe <hi>blinde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> when there is no ſuch thing? Looke vp to <hi>Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> There is the <hi>ſeate of Maieſtie,</hi> whereon <hi>he</hi> ſitteth, who ordereth all thy loſſes. Be patient towards <hi>him. He</hi> is the <hi>Lord.</hi> How knoweſt thou, whether <hi>hee</hi> will not deale with thee, as <hi>he</hi> dealt with <hi>Iob, cha. 42.12?</hi> It may be, hee will make thy <hi>latter ende,</hi> better then thy <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> was. Forget not therefore what now thou haſt learned,
<q>Whatſoever affliction befalleth any one any where in this world, it is from the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Is it from the LORD? Here then in the fourth place we haue, wherewith to comfort our ſelues in the day of <hi>affliction.</hi> Whatſoever <hi>affliction</hi> ſhall befall vs, its fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the LORD: the LORD he is <hi>omnipotent,</hi> he is <hi>merciful,</hi> he is <hi>ever preſent</hi> with vs; <hi>he will not ſuffer</hi> vs <hi>to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue</hi> our <hi>abilities; but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape,</hi> that wee <hi>may be able to beare it.</hi> So ſaith <hi>S. Paule, 1. Cor. 10.13.</hi> Well: we may be <hi>troubled on every ſide,</hi> but we ſhall not be <hi>overpreſſed;</hi> we may bee <hi>perplexed,</hi> but ſhall not be <hi>in deſpaire;</hi> we may be <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted,</hi> but ſhall not be <hi>forſaken;</hi> wee may be <hi>caſt downe,</hi> but ſhall not bee <hi>deſtroyed.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs hereof, <hi>2. Cor. 4.8.</hi> Say, it is our caſe. Wee are <hi>troubled, perplexed, perſecuted, caſt downe;</hi> what ſhall wee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14545:13"/> doe? Wee will ſupport our ſelues with <hi>Davids</hi> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>Pſal. 23.4. Though</hi> we <hi>walke through the valley of the ſhaddow of death,</hi> we <hi>wil feare no evil; for thou</hi> LORD, <hi>art with</hi> vs. Thou, LORD art with vs;<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>Quis contra nos?</hi> We<note n="ſ" place="margin">Hebr. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>will not feare,</hi> what man can doe vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to conclude, ſith there is no <hi>affliction, that befalleth any man in this world,</hi> but it's from the LORD; and he is a <hi>baſtard,</hi> not a <hi>ſonne,</hi> that is not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of <hi>afflictions,</hi> as the author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>chap. 12.8.</hi> Let vs with <hi>S. Iames, chap. 1.2.</hi> account it <hi>exceeding ioy,</hi> when <hi>we are afflicted.</hi> The <hi>Patriarches,</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> haue found the way to Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> narrow, rugged, and bloody: and ſhall <hi>wee</hi> thinke that God will ſtrew carpets for <hi>our nice feete</hi> to walke thither? He that is the <hi>dore,</hi> and the <hi>way,</hi> our LORD &amp; <hi>Saviour, Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> hath by his owne example taught vs, that by many afflictions we muſt enter into the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. There is but one paſſage thither; and it is a ſtrait one. If with much preſſure we can get through, and leaue but our ſuperfluous rags, as torne from vs, in the throng, we ſhall be happy.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore, whenſoever any adverſity, croſſe, calamity, miſerie, or affliction ſhall betide vs, let vs with due regard to the hand, that ſmiteth vs, <hi>receiue it</hi> with thankes, <hi>keepe it</hi> with patience, <hi>digeſt it</hi> in hope, <hi>apply it</hi> with wiſedome, <hi>bury it</hi> with meditation, and doubtleſſe it ſhall <hi>end vnto vs</hi> in peace and glory, in peace of Conſcience in this life, and in glory eternall in the higheſt Heavens. Of this <hi>peace of Conſcience</hi> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14545:14"/> this life, and that <hi>immarceſſible crowne of glory</hi> in the life to come, vouchſafe gracious Father, to make vs all partakers for thy beſt beloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake: to whom with thee in the vnitie of the Holy Spirit be all praiſe and power, might and Maieſtie, dignitie and dominion for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14545:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
